As a software developer and technologist,
كمُطور برمجيات وتقني
I've worked on a number of civic technology projects
عملتُ على عدة مشاريع تكنلوجية مدنية
over the years.
على مر السنين
Civic tech is sometimes referred to as tech for good,
التكنولوجيا المدنية في بعض الأحيان يشار إليها بالتكنولوجيا الخيرة،
using technology to solve humanitarian problems.
باستخدام التكنولوجيا لحل المشكلات الإنسانية.
This is in 2010 in Uganda,
هذه في أوغندا عام 2010م
working on a solution that allowed local populations
أثناء عملي لإيجاد حل يسمح للسكان المحليين
to avoid government surveillance on their mobile phones
بتجنب الرقابة الحكومية على هواتفهم النقالة.
for expressing dissent.
بسبب تعبيرهم عن معارضتهم
That same technology was deployed later in North Africa
تم نشر هذه التكنولوجيا نفسها لاحقًا في شمال أفريقيا
for similar purposes to help activists stay connected
لأغراض مماثلة، تساعد الناشطين على التواصل
when governments were deliberately shutting off connectivity
حينما تتعمد الحكومات إلى قطع التواصل
as a means of population control.
كوسيلة للسيطرة على الشعب
But over the years, as I have thought about these technologies
لكن مع مر السنين، كانت لدي أفكار حول تلك التكنلوجيا،
and the things that I work on,
والمشاريع التي عملتُ عليها
a question kind of nags in the back of my mind, which is,
هنالك سؤال يتردد في ذهني، وهو:
what if we're wrong about the virtues of technology,
ما إذا كنا مخطئين حول فضائل التكنولوجيا،
and if it sometimes actively hurts
وإذا كان في بعض الأحيان يضر بنشاط
the communities that we're intending to help?
تلك المجتمعات التي ننوي بمساعدتها؟
The tech industry around the world tends to operate under similar assumptions
صناعة التكنولوجيا في جميع أنحاء العالم تميل إلى العمل في ظل افتراضات مماثلة
that if we build great things,
هذا إن قُمنا ببناء أشياء عظيمة
it will positively affect everyone.
فسوف تؤثر على كل شخص بشكل إيجابي.
Eventually, these innovations will get out and find everyone.
حتمًا، هذه الابتكارات ستخرج للعلن وتكون في متناول الكل.
But that's not always the case.
ولكن تلك ليست الحالة دائمًا.
I like to call this blind championing of technology "trickle-down techonomics,"
أود تسميتها المناصرة العمياء للتكنلوجيا "الكل يستفيد اقتصاديا من التكنولوجيا"
to borrow a phrase. (Laughter)
العبارة مُستعارة. (ضحك)
We tend to think that if we design things for the select few,
نميل إلى الاعتقاد بأنه إذا قُمنا بتصميم أشياء لقلة مختارة،
eventually those technologies will reach everyone,
في النهاية كل تلك التكنولوجيا سوف تصل للجميع،
and that's not always the case.
وهذه ليست الحالة دائمًا.
Technology and innovation behaves a lot like wealth and capital.
سلوكيات التكنولوجيا والابتكار مِثل الثروة ورأس المال.
They tend to consolidate in the hands of the few,
إنها تميل إلى الترسخ في أيدي قلة من الناس
and sometimes they find their way out into the hands of the many.
وأحيانًا تجد طريقها لأيدي الكثيرين.
And so most of you aren't tackling oppressive regimes on the weekends,
الكثير منكم لا يتبع حميات قاسية في عطلة نهاية الأسبوع
so I wanted to think of a few examples that might be a little bit more relatable.
أردت التفكير في أمثلة ليكون الموضوع أكثر ترابطًا
In the world of wearables and smartphones and apps,
في عالم الإلكترونيات الملبوسة والهواتف الذكية والتطبيقات،
there's a big movement to track people's personal health
توجد توجهات كبيرة لمتابعة الصحة الشخصية للناس
with applications that track the number of calories that you burn
كالتطبيقات التي تحسب عدد السعرات الحرارية التي تحرقها
or whether you're sitting too much or walking enough.
أو ما إذا كنت جالسًا أكثر من اللازم أو أنك مشيت بما فيه الكفاية.
These technologies make patient intake in medical facilities much more efficient,
هذه التقنيات تجعل وصف حالة المرضى في المرافق الطبية أكثر فعالية،
are starting to expect these types of efficiencies.
على استعداد لتقبل كل هذه الأنواع من الكفاءات.
As these digital tools find their way into medical rooms,
ولما كانت هذه الأدوات الرقمية قد وجدت طريقها إلى الغرف الطبية،
and they become digitally ready,
وأصبحت جاهزة رقميًا،
what happens to the digitally invisible?
ما الذي سيحدث للرقميات غير المرئية؟
What does the medical experience look like
كيف تبدو الخبرة الطبية وما الذي تعنيه؟
for someone who doesn't have the $400 phone or watch
لشخص لا يملك 400 $ لشراء جوال أو ساعة.
tracking their every movement?
تتعقب كل تحركاتهم؟
Do they now become a burden on the medical system?
وهل أصبح هؤلاء عبئًا على النظام الطبي؟
Is their experience changed?
هل تجربتهم تغيرت؟
In the world of finance, Bitcoin and crypto-currencies
في عالم الأموال، العملة الإلكترونية وتزوير العملات
are revolutionizing the way we move money around the world,
هنالك ثورة نوعية لتحريك المال حول العالم.
but the challenge with these technologies
ولكن التحدي مع هذه التقنيات
is the barrier to entry is incredibly high, right?
هو أن حاجز الدخول عالي وبشكل لا يصدق، أليس كذلك؟
You need access to the same phones, devices, connectivity,
تحتاج إلى الدخول لكل الهواتف والأجهزة والاتصالات،
and even where you don't, where you can find a proxy agent,
وحتى في الحالات التي لم تقم بذلك، يمكنك العثور على وكيل بروكسي،
usually they require a certain amount of capital to participate.
عادة ما يتطلب قدرا معينًا من رأس المال للمشاركة فيها.
using paper notes when the rest of the world moves to digital currency?
الذي يستخدم الورق، بينما بقية العالم تحولوا إلى العملة الرقمية؟
Another example from my hometown in Philadelphia:
مثال آخر من مدينتي فيلادلفيا:
I recently went to the public library there,
ذهبتُ مؤخرًا إلى المكتبة العامة هناك،
and they are facing an existential crisis.
وعلمت أن المكتبات تواجه أزمة.
Public funding is dwindling,
التمويل العام يتضاءل،
they have to reduce their footprint to stay open and stay relevant,
وجب عليهم تقليص إمكانياتهم من أجل أن تبقى مفتوحة ومتواصلة
and so one of the ways they're going about this
وإحدى الطرق التي نفذوها هي
is digitizing a number of the books and moving them to the cloud.
ترقيم عدد من الكتب ونقلها إلى أنظمة حاسوبية.
This is great for most kids. Right?
وهذا رائع بالنسبة لأغلب الأطفال. أليس كذلك؟
You can check out books from home,
يمكن متابعة الكتب من المنزل،
you can research on the way to school or from school,
يمكن إجراء بحث في الطريق للمدرسة أو أثناء العودة،
but these are really two big assumptions,
ولكن في الحقيقة هما افتراضان
that one, you have access at home,
الأول، إمكانية الولوج من المنزل
and two, that you have access to a mobile phone,
الثاني، إمكانية الولوج من الهاتف النقال
and in Philadelphia, many kids do not.
وفي فيلادلفيا، العديد من الأطفال لا يمكنهم ذلك
So what does their education experience look like
لذا ما الذي تبدو عليه تجربتهم التعليمية
in the wake of a completely cloud-based library,
في أعقاب الاعتماد الكلي على المكتبة السحابية.
what used to be considered such a basic part of education?
والذي كانت تعتبر ركنًا أساسيًا في التعليم؟
How do they stay competitive?
كيف يبقون في المنافسة؟
A final example from across the world in East Africa:
مثال أخير عبر العالم من شرق أفريقيا:
there's been a huge movement to digitize land ownership rights,
هُنالك توجه ضخم لترقيم حقوق امتلاك الأراضي،
for a number of reasons.
لعدة أسباب،
Migrant communities, older generations dying off,
المجتمعات المهاجرة، والأجيال القديمة في مرحلة الزوال
and ultimately poor record-keeping
وبصورة حتمية سوء حفظ السجلات
have led to conflicts over who owns what.
أدى إلى صراعات حول الملكية
And so there was a big movement to put all this information online,
ولذا هنالك تحرك كبير لوضع تلك المعلومات على الانترنت
to track all the ownership of these plots of land,
لتتبع كل المالكين لقطع الأراضي
put them in the cloud, and give them to the communities.
وضعهم على الحاسوب وتقديمهم للمجتمع
But actually, the unintended consequence of this
لكن في الواقع، ونتيجة غير مقصودة لهذا
has been that venture capitalists, investors, real estate developers,
أن أصحاب رؤوس الأموال، المستثمرين والمطورين العقاريين،
have swooped in and they've begun buying up these plots of land
بدأوا في التدفق بكميات كبيرة لشراء تلك الأراضي
right out from under these communities,
من أيدي السكان المحليين
because they have access to the technologies
لأن لديهم إمكانية الوصول إلى هذه التكنولوجيا،
and the connectivity that makes that possible.
والقدرة على الوصول إليها.
So that's the common thread that connects these examples,
كل تلك الأمثلة تجمعهم قواسم المشتركة،
the unintended consequences of the tools and the technologies that we make.
هي العواقب غير المقصودة من الأدوات والتقنيات التي أنشأناها.
As engineers, as technologists,
كمهندسين، وفنيين،
We think more about doing things than the outcomes of what we are doing.
نحن نريد أن نفعل الأشياء، لا نُفكر في نتائج هذه المسألة.
This needs to change.
وهذا يجب تغييره.
We have a responsibility to think about the outcomes of the technologies we build,
يقع على عاتقنا التفكير في أبعاد ما نصنعه من تكنلوجيا
especially as they increasingly control the world in which we live.
خاصة بتزايد إحكامها على العالم الذي نعيش فيه.
In the late '90s,
في أواخر التسعينيات،
there was a big push for ethics in the world of investment and banking.
كان هناك تعزيز كبير للأخلاق في عالم الاستثمار والأعمال المصرفية.
I think in 2014, we're long overdue for a similar movement
أعتقد أنه في عام 2014، قد تأخرنا كثيرًا عن بدء حركة مماثلة
in the area of tech and technology.
في مجال التقنية والتكنولوجيا.
So, I just encourage you, as you are all thinking about the next big thing,
لذا، أنا فقط أشجعكم، على التفكير في الخطوة القدمة
as entrepreneurs, as CEOs, as engineers, as makers,
كأصحاب مشاريع، ومدراء تنفيذيين، كمهندسين، وصناع،
that you think about the unintended consequences
بالنظر في تبعات النتائج غير المقصودة
of the things that you're building,
للأشياء التي نصنعها
because the real innovation is in finding ways to include everyone.
لأن الإبداع الحقيقي هو إيجاد طرق لشمل الجميع.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)